A Guide to the Gordon and Webster Family Papers
University of Virginia Library
- Series I: Armistead Churchill Gordon, Jr.
  - Subseries B. General Correspondence (Box-folder 2:1-11:6)
    - 19331943 General correspondence Armistead Churchill Gordon and John Cook Wyllie, 3 items (Box-folder 2:3)
      Armistead mentioned that John Hartwell Cocke was not adept at poetry or humor but was a "prolific scribe." He also wrote about local gossip and news of marriages such as, [Shepperson] and Philippa Bruce. There is a letter from John Cook Wyllie about being in the Signal corps and "secret weapon balderdash"
    - 19441952 General correspondence Armistead Churchill Gordon and James Southall Wilson, 4 items (Box-folder 2:4)
      There is a thank you letter to Ann Gordon from James Southall Wilson signed "her godfather;" Southall wrote to Armistead about his teaching in the English Department at Louisiana State University; about Jack Hunter's reward for his work on Shakespeare; politics in the state of Louisiana and the state support for Eisenhower. Others mentioned are Nathan Coffe, Professor Kirby, Watson, and Joan Miller.
    - 1916 September 23 General correspondence: John Armstrong Chaloner to Mrs. [Maria] Gordon, 1 item (Box-folder 2:5)
      There is a letter from John Armstrong Chaloner in which he wrote that he wanted to increase his visits to the Gordon clan for supper but not to stay for long discussions afterwards. He was concerned that his "unusual" mental state not be exposed to anyone. He also mentioned his lawsuit being almost over so that he could focus on writing romances and reading his manuscripts to the Gordon's.
    - 1943-1969 General Correspondence Cornelia Waddell Gordon, 6 items (Box-folder 2:6)
      There is a 1953 letter from Cornelia to Mrs. Eleanore Webster ("Harry's mother) alluding to Ann's miscarriage of their second child, Susan Webster. She died before delivery.
    - 1931-1932 General correspondence: Death of Armistead Churchill Gordon, Sr., 28 items (Box-folder 2:7)
      There are sympathy letters and acknowledgements to Armistead Churchill Gordon, Jr. regarding his father's death. There is a resolution made by the University of Virginia in honor of Gordon. Also included are letters from Harry Clemons; John B. Jenkins, Jr.; Mrs. Edwin Anderson Alderman; Dumas Malone; Meno Lovenstein; William Cabell Bruce; Susie M. E. Smith; William Draper Lewis; Pipe Wright; William P. Trent; George Gordon Battle; R. H. Dabney; Agnes Symmers; J. M. Bulloch; James W. Vander Voort; Tazewell Taylor, Jr.; John J. Meara; Temple Bodley; George H. Denny; Alex Dumas; George Fawcett; Frank [ ] Washington and Lee; James P. C. Southall; [James K. Sylliers;] Hugh H. Young; and the Board of Supervisors for Augusta County. There are also letters about a portrait of Gordon for his courtroom.
    - 1897-1946n.d. General correspondence: letters to the Gordon family, 58 items (Box-folder 2:8)
      Cousin Alberta J. Gillingham wrote to Mary Gordon asking for help in preventing(Alberta's) estate and gold mine from being sold for nothing during the depression (January 1932;) and a negative response from Mary is included. There is correspondence with Nell Battle Lewis and Mary Gordon; and various thank you letters and postcards from friends and family including Cornelia's sister, Margaret
    - 1920-1924 General correspondence regarding dissertation (permission to publish poetry), 83 items (Box-folder 2:9)
      Armistead Gordon wrote to various publishers and colleagues in an attempt to ask Virginia authors for permission to publish selections of their verse in his book. There is a letter from his father advising him on the legal aspect of copyright. Included are James Branch Cabell, Thomas Nelson Page, William Peterfield Trent (with original poems), Amelié Rives Troubetzkoy (attached is an original unpublished poem titled "To Death,") William Cabell Bruce, Phillip Alexander Bruce, Nancy Byrd Turner, Beverly D. Tucker, Virginia T. McCormick, C. Alphonso Smith; Evan R. Chesterman; E. G. Swem; James P. Nelson; Robert M. Hughes; Lyon G. Tyler; Mary Page Bird; J. L. Hall; Rosewell Page; William [Counscon;] Frank P. Brent; Katharine Pearson Woods; Kate Langley Bosher; George Wayne Anderson; [Clonway] Baker; A. L. McWhelan; Mary Johnston; Fairfax Harrison; R. A. McCabe; Benjamin Sled; Edward V. Valentine; C. M. Newman; James Thomley Clarke; R. T. W. Duke, Jr.; Henry T. Touthan; John S. Patton; C. W. Coleman; Thomas Lomax Hunter; G. T. Snead; Ellen Seawell; Josephine Johnson; John Ruffin; G. W. Moreland, Henry Holt; and various publishers.
    - 1921-1925 General correspondence regarding dissertation ("Virginian Writers of Fugitive Verse"), 71 items (Box-folder 2:10)
      Most of the correspondence is between his editorial supervisor, James B. Kenyon for James T. White & Co. and Armistead Churchill Gordon, Jr. There are also letters from Armistead Churchill Gordon, Sr. advising Armistead on the publication and contract. Other correspondents include William Peterfield Trent; Thomas Nelson Page and his introduction for the book; Raymond P. Barnes; Jim Stephens; Thomas Lomax Hunter; William Cabell Bruce; M. Page Bird; and Landon C. Bell (and several typewritten poems) Also included are miscellaneous poems by James Alston Cabell.
    - 1924-1952 General correspondence regarding publications by Armistead Churchill Gordon, 36 items (Box-folder 3:1)
      Gordon wrote about his reviews, and future writing projects. Correspondents include William Cabell Bruce; Clifford Smyth, Literary Digest International Book Review; W. C. Stouffer, The Roanoke Times; George Herbert Clarke; Ellen Seawell; Alexander Wilbourne Weddell; John Lloyd Newcomb, Virginia E. Savidge, (about writing a biography of John Hartwell Cocke;) He also gave advice to Miss Pearl Gayton on her sketch of Robert E. Lee. He also corresponded with Clarence R. Stone, Southern Life and Literature series; Nash Burger regarding reviews for the New York Times Book Review; Charles A. Ford, John C. Winston Company regarding authorship of textbooks for Virginia School Children; Atcheson Hench and Roy Land (about withdrawing an introduction for James Southall Wilson's book). Included with correspondence, is a manuscript "In Honor of James Southall Wilson" by Armistead Churchill Gordon, Jr.
    - 1930-1938 General correspondence regarding publication of Armistead Gordon's "George Mason", 24 items (Box-folder 3:2)
      There is correspondence between Armistead Churchill Gordon, Jr. and Duke University Press concerning the publication of his father's manuscript on George Mason. After Duke Press asked Gordon, Jr, to correct four volumes of the manuscript, and Gordon complied, the Duke Press claimed that they did not have the funds to publish it due to the depression.
    - 1914-1926 General correspondence regarding publications for Mary Gordon, 10 items (Box-folder 3:3)
      There are rejection notices from McClure's Magazine, Charles Scribner's Sons; F. Graham Cootes; Harper & Brothers; and The Dial
    - 1933-1953 General correspondence: Reference letters by Armistead Churchill Gordon, Jr., 122 items (Box-folder 3:4)
    - 19301948 VIP correspondence, 2 items (Box-folder 3:5)
      Included is a letter from Henry W. Holt to Mary Gordon thanking her for her note when he was sick. There is also a letter from Armistead Gordon Jr. to William "Bill" Tuck pleading against the appointment of Wiliam S. Hildreth for the Board of Visitors vacancy.
    - 18921907-1910n. d. General correspondence Waddells, 15 items (Box-folder 3:6)
    - 18831894-1912n. d. Gordon family correspondence, 14 items (Box-folder 3:7)
      There are letters from Armistead Gordon, Sr. to hi wife, Maria, and their children. Also included are letters from his brother, Uncle James Lindsay Gordon, to the the children. John Armstrong Chaloner is mentioned throughout the family correspondence from 1912 to 1923.
    - 1913 Gordon family correspondence, 16 items (Box-folder 3:8)
      Armistead Gordon, Jr. wrote to his family about life at William and Mary College.
    - 1914 January-August Gordon family correspondence, 20 items (Box-folder 3:9)
      There are more letters from Armistead Gordon, Jr. about college life.
    - 1914 September-October Gordon family correspondence, 15 items (Box-folder 3:10)
      James Gordon wrote to his family about life at the University of Virginia. References are made to Ada Bantz Beardsworth, Dr. Edwin Anderson Alderman's return from Europe, and enthusiasm for the Yale football game.
    - 1914 November-December Gordon family correspondence, 21 items (Box-folder 4:1)
      There are letters from Armistead Churchill Gordon, Sr. to his wife Maria, and letters from their children, Margaret, James, Armistead, and George. There are references to Armistead Churchill Gordon, Sr.'s literary piece, "Baytop" ("Ommirandy") which was published in Scribner's Magazine in May, 1915.
    - 1915 January-March Gordon family correspondence, 20 items (Box-folder 4:2)
      There are descriptions of various professors such as C. Alphonso Smith in which James Gordon wrote, "[Smith's ]line of drool is getting so familiar as to be gummy;" and he wrote that Chuckie Kent "jumps up and down like a pea on a hot shovel"(January 11, 1915).
    - 1915 April-September Gordon family correspondence, 17 items (Box-folder 4:3)
      Armistead and James mentioned their fraternities and classes at William and Mary and the University of Virginia.
    - 1915 October Gordon family correspondence, 25 items (Box-folder 4:4)
      Armistead Gordon's mother mentioned hearing John Powell play his music (while she was visiting Colonel Gordon McCabe in Richmond, October 15, 1915) She also wrote that Colonel McCabe was happy about a cotton business deal with England; James had a story published called "The Princess, the Tower, and the Councilors' Beards" with illustrations by Mary Gordon; John Armstrong Chaloner wrote about visiting the Gordons (October 22, 1915).
    - 1915 November-December Gordon family correspondence, 8 items (Box-folder 4:5)
      Armistead mentioned playing football for William and Mary and discussed his courses and asked about family visits with John Armstrong Chaloner. James and Armistead mentioned reading their father's poem and thought it very good.
    - 1916 January-July Gordon family correspondence, 31 items (Box-folder 4:6)
      Armistead wrote to Mary about John Armstrong Chaloner and mentioned Mary's illustrations for Corks and Curls. He also wrote about campaigns to raise money for Robert Gooch to drive ambulances in France; and sending "Wild Bill Brockman" from Madison Hall to China. James wrote that DuPont was planning to build a plant in Williamsburg. Also mentioned is the "grippe" and that George was sick.
    - 1917 January-June Gordon family correspondence, 25 items (Box-folder 4:7)
      There are letters from Margaret Gordon to her family while she and her mother visited their cousins at Natural Bridge. James worked at the Valley Tire and Lumber branch and Gordon was working for the Virginian Power Company in Cabin Creek, West Virginia during the summer. Correspondence shows that Gordon received a Cary Isaac scholarship for his next session of school. James was working for the tie company in Washington D. C. and mentioned various topics such as “suffragettes,” and Union strikes. Margaret wrote about their father visiting the McCabes and the estimated height required to be drafted for the war. Mary wrote Armistead teasing him about girls and sleeping late and George wrote about his life at home as a “worm” and all the trouble everyone gave him about his chores.
    - 1917 July-August Gordon family correspondence, 28 items (Box-folder 4:8)
      James wrote about his automobile, working in Washington D. C., and Norfolk, prohibition, and the official instructions for the draft (which required a weight between 166 and 214 pounds for a height of six foot three and that would make him too light-to the delight of his family). Armistead received a raise as a dispatcher, and was selecting a roommate for George at William and Mary for the following year. Other topics mentioned are their father’s work to be published, “Omirandy Stories,” and the infantile paralysis (polio) quarantine.
    - 1917 September-October Gordon family correspondence, 17 items (Box-folder 5:1)
      Mentioned is a conversation between Armistead Gordon, Sr. and Philip Bruce about the “degeneracy of the students at the University in the last decade.” Also included is Armistead’s brother, George Gordon’s witty commentary on not needing a degree and his dislike for the Germans. George also wrote that their sister, Margaret was suffering from nervous spells again. Armistead wrote that the University of Virginia students were upset that the library was not open in the evenings and that “Tony” [Alderman] refused to open it. Armistead wondered if his father or the Board of Directors had heard about it.
    - 1917 November-December Gordon family correspondence, 24 items (Box-folder 5:2)
      Topics include George being annoyed by his roommate, shortages of sugar, the draft, drill marches, uniforms, and Professor Leonidas Whipple. James moved to Lexington North Carolina as part of his job with the Valley Tie and Lumber Company and liked it very much. Armistead was staying at Stonefield, enjoyed the quiet home like atmosphere and mentioned a loan from Mr. Carruthers. Armistead Sr. warned that the country was going to be facing hard economic times.
    - 1918 January-April Gordon family correspondence, 31 items (Box-folder 5:3)
      James was paying for Armistead to attend classes at UVA (for graduate school). Armistead’s mother mentioned her husband’s work on “An Account of Jefferson Davis’s Life.” She also mentioned John Chaloner’s trip to New York. George and James wrote about the impact that the war was having on William and Mary and the University of Virginia. On March 13, 1918, Armistead’s sister, Margaret, who had been admitted to Western State Hospital and was recovering from her “nervous collapses” wrote to their father, “that, if you take me home, I won’t run away any more,-never, never, never! Woman’s place is home, and I was a vain foolish girl not to realize it.”
    - 1918 May-July Gordon family correspondence, 38 items (Box-folder 5:4)
      May 17, 1919 Armistead's father wrote (to his wife) that Mary visited Margaret at Western State Hospital. James was stationed at St. Helena Training Station, Norfolk and to the cargo ship, U.S.S. Rynland (name changed to Rijnland). Armistead got a job in Norfolk at the Naval Base and was later assigned to the 36 th Company, at Camp Lee, Virginia.
    - 1918 August-December Gordon family correspondence, 54 items (Box-folder 5:5)
      Armistead mentioned that his unit was quarantined due to the Spanish flu; his brother George died, (ill- September 23, death mentioned (tetanus?) on November 7) Armistead was transferred from the hospital detail in the Casual Detachment Department to the Gas and Flame division in the Chemical War Service Department where he worked at the felt plant in Boston, Massachusetts. James was in France with the U. S. S. Rynland (November 12)
    - 1919 January-April Gordon family correspondence, 43 items (Box-folder 5:6)
      January 19, 1919 Armistead was discharged from the war, visited his family in Staunton for a few weeks and was attending classes at the University of Virginia and James resumed his job in Lexington, N.C.
    - 1919 May-December Gordon family correspondence, 53 items (Box-folder 6:1)
      Armistead's mother wrote that Mary had a children's book published ("The Chrystal Ball;") She also mentioned that Armistead Gordon, Sr. sold "Dagger of D'Aubrey" to the Country Gentlemen. Armistead (Sr.) went with George Michie to see the George Rogers Clark Statue, and John Armstrong Chaloner described a play he had written on being in an asylum.
    - 1920 January-June Gordon family correspondence, 26 items (Box-folder 6:2)
      Letters mention a lack of coal, that many people had the flu, that ACG, Sr. was elected President of the Virginia State Bar Association, and the death of Captain Gordon McCabe.
    - 1920 July-December Gordon family correspondence, 22 items (Box-folder 6:3)
      Armistead wrote that Dr. Bruce was working on his centennial history of the University of Virginia, and James marriage to Adelaide Hargrave took place on November 10th (Newspaper clipping of the wedding included.)
    - 1921 January-July Gordon family correspondence, 17 items (Box-folder 6:4)
      Armistead gave chapters of his dissertation, “Virginian Writers of Fugitive Poetry” to his father to read and his father wrote him back with praise and suggestions. Armistead Sr. wrote letters to his wife, “Ria” while she was vacationing at Atlantic City. He mentioned that there were mostly Jews there and the “Hebrew children have taken possession there as everywhere else on this country.”
    - 1921 August-December Gordon family correspondence, 48 items (Box-folder 6:5)
      Armistead’s mother vacationed at Atlantic City. Armistead received his Ph.D. and was sending his manuscript (dissertation) to publishers. He was courting Cornelia Waddell. James described poor financial conditions of the banks, schools and farming in Lexington, N. C.
    - 1922 Gordon family correspondence, 48 items (Box-folder 6:6)
      Armistead wrote that the fate of the UVA medical school was in the hands of the Senate since the House was trying to pass a bill to have it moved to Richmond. Armistead married Cornelia Waddell (wedding invitation included). Tom Page wrote an introduction for Armistead’s dissertation. Armistead was working on biographical sketches of Robert Eden Scot, John Daly Brock, and William Henry Brodmax. Armistead was made Associate Professor and was paid eighteen hundred dollars per year. Armistead Churchill Gordon, Sr. was working on the life of Gordon McCabe. Attached to a letter are news clippings about Gordon family genealogy for Armistead Churchill Gordon, Sr.
    - 1923 Gordon family correspondence, 42 items (Box-folder 7:1)
      James T. White & Co. published Armistead’s dissertation, “Virginian Writers of Fugitive Poetry.” There is a newspaper clipping about John Armstrong Chaloner from James Gordon. Armistead wrote about the differences in teaching women students, and the publication of his volume. Their mother went on a vacation in Atlantic City.
    - 1924 January-July Gordon family correspondence, 20 items (Box-folder 7:2)
      James wrote that his wife, Adelaide, had bobbed her hair “along with the rest of the flappers.” Armistead and his father wrote about the reviews of his recently published dissertation, including a thank you letter to Dr. Woodberry.
    - 1924 August-December Gordon family correspondence, 23 items (Box-folder 7:3)
      Armistead described his attitude toward some students when he wrote, "…arguing myself blue in the face with a few of the Northern gentry (mostly of the tribe of Israel)" who he described as being too ambitious for their own good. Armistead Churchill Gordon, Sr. finished his book on William Gordon McCabe. There are also letters about the death of Cornelia's father, James Nelson Waddell and an obituary.
    - 1925 Gordon family correspondence, 30 items (Box-folder 7:4)
      Armistead was busy with his classes, biographical essays, reviews, and his textbook of essays. Armistead’s father advised him to not be critical in his book reviews because it would make him have enemies.
    - Gordon family correspondence 1926, 35 items (Box-folder 7:5)
      Armistead was working with Dr. Metcalf on the “Library of Southern Literature.” Armistead Churchill Gordon, Sr. had “Gordon McCabe” published. He also mentioned his work on “Allegra.”Armistead wrote to his father about Dumas Malone’s negative review of “Gordon McCabe” and mentioned that Dr. James Southall Wilson should have let Dr. Bruce write the review instead of Malone. Also mentioned are Reddy Echols, and Ivey Lewis. Armistead wrote his mother that he got a raise in salary to twenty five hundred dollars per year. Armistead’s father mentioned a ceremony at Monticello honoring [Claude G.] Bowers with the Jefferson medal and remarked that Dr. Philip Bruce’s “History of the University” was more deserving of the award. Armistead’s father complained that the University of Virginia was not committed to the needs of the library. James Gordon bought out the Valley Tie & Lumber Company in Lexington, North Carolina.
    - 1927 Gordon family correspondence, 25 items (Box-folder 7:6)
      Armistead and his father corresponded about biographical sketches, and books that they were reading. Armistead’s mother visited James and her grandchildren in Lexington N.C.
    - 1928 Gordon family correspondence, 14 items (Box-folder 8:1)
      Armistead and Cornelia sailed to France and England on the S.S. Olympic of the White Star Line and wrote about their travels.
    - 1929 Gordon family correspondence, 24 items (Box-folder 8:2)
      Armistead wrote that he was very busy with teaching at UVA and extension courses in Richmond, and that it took from twelve to fourteen hours a day to prepare for lectures. He continued to send his biographical sketches to his father for suggestions. Ann Gordon was born in May. Armistead Churchill Gordon, Sr. was working on a biography of George Mason. The health of Dr. Philip Bruce was mentioned, as was a visit from Mr. and Mrs. James Alston Cabell, and the suicide of Bruce Williams.
    - 1930 January-May Gordon family correspondence, 34 items (Box-folder 8:3)
      Armistead received sympathy from Dr. Paul and Anna Barringer, Dr. Metcalf, Ivey Lewis, Albert Balz and many others regarding his mother’s death. (March 11, 1930) Armistead mentioned John Cook Wyllie and his research of the Staunton River and how Staunton got its name from William Byrd. Armistead Churchill Gordon, Sr. finished his book on the Shenandoah Valley and was starting “The Red Hills of Piedmont.” Armistead wrote that Nell Lewis had been very ill but had improved. Gordon, Sr. wrote about the rumors that Fred Scott was named Rector of the University because he was giving the money for the athletic field. He also mentioned Edwin Anderson Alderman, Founders Day and needing money for the library. There were student riots against the prices of the movie theaters. Mrs Paul Goodloe McIntire told Armistead that they made three thousand dollars on the Garden Club of Virginia’s book on historic Virginia gardens. Also included is a description of Dr. Barringer; comments about the Hoover economy and a news clipping about the library receiving money for Virginian materials.
    - 1930 June-December Gordon family correspondence, 34 items (Box-folder 8:4)
      Armistead wrote that he had been given the assignment to write a biography of the Reverend John William Jones. He also mentioned meeting Fred Scott and wrote criticisms of Scott for donating to athletics instead of the library. He also described his theory that Jefferson substituted tobacco leaves for classical acanthus on the capitals of the columns of the Rotunda but it turned out to be untrue. (Also mentioned are the Board Meeting Minutes of the University of Virginia on the restoration of the Rotunda June 18, 1902) Another research project that he discussed was whether it was Jack Jouett Sr. or Jr. that warned Jefferson that the British were coming. He also wrote to his father that Dean “Billy” Thornton was having his leg amputated. James wrote about his businesses closing down due to the depression (November 24, 1930) and Armistead mentioned that people were knocking on his door and begging for food.
    - 1931 Gordon family correspondence, 20 items (Box-folder 8:5)